Finding Aid for Marcus L. Plant Papers, 1949-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Marcus L. Plant papers 1949-1980
Plant, Marcus L.,1911-
8 linear feet
85369 Aa 2
Professor of law at the University of Michigan and member of the University's Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics. Papers include files relating to his involvement in university athletics, notably as the faculty representative to the Big Ten Conference, as member of the National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA), and member of the U. S. Olympic Committee; also materials concerning university hockey, especially the Western Intercollegiate Hockey Association; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor number 6768 ) came to the library in April 1982.
The collection is open without restriction.
Marcus L. Plant was born in New London, Wisconsin, on November 10, 1911. He received his BA (1932) and MA (1934) from Lawrence College and his JD (1938) from the University of Michigan. He entered a private law firm in Milwaukee (1938-1844) and then in New York City (1944-1946) before becoming a member of the law faculty of the University of Michigan. Plant was a member of the faculty from 1946 until his retirement in 1982
While at the University of Michigan, Plant developed strong ties to Michigan's Athletic Department, the Big Ten Conference, and various regional and national associations representing amateur athletics. At the University of Michigan he was a member of the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics (1949-1979) and served as Michigan's Faculty Representative to the Big Ten Conference (1955-1979). He was secretary of the Big Ten faculty representatives from 1956 to 1979. A member of the NCAA since 1955, Plant served as the NCAA's President from 1967 to 1969 and as a member of the Executive Committee from 1970 to 1979. In addition, Plant was a member of the United States Olympic Committee from 1969 to 1972
The papers are arranged according to the filing system developed by Plant. The six major series of his records include Athletics at the University of Michigan; Big Ten Conference; National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA); Western Intercollegiate Hockey League; Western Collegiate Hockey Association; and United States Olympic Committee.
Subjects:
Athletics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Hockey--United States.; Intercollegiate Conference of Faculty Representatives.; National Collegiate Athletic Association.; United States Olympic Committee.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan. Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics.; University of Michigan--Football.; Western Intercollegiate Hockey League.; Western Collegiate Hockey Association.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Plant, Marcus L., 1911-1984; University of Michigan--Law School.; University of Michigan--Law School--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Law School--Anniversaries, etc.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- University of Michigan
  The records relating to athletics at the University of Michigan consist of Plant's files during the years he was a member of the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics (1949-1979). These files include annual reports and minutes of the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics; correspondence with University of Michigan Presidents Harlan Hatcher and Robben Fleming and with the Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs; and records relating to scholastic eligibility of student-athletes at the University.
  - Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics
    - Annual Reports
      - 1950-1959 (Box 1)
        [1-1]
      - 1960-1968 (Box 1)
        [1-2]
      - 1969-1979 (except 1978) (Box 1)
        [1-3]
    - Manual (Box 1)
      [1-4]
    - Minutes
      - 1949-1953 (Box 1)
        [1-5]
      - 1953-1959 (Box 1)
        [1-6]
      - 1960-1963 (Box 1)
        [1-7]
      - 1964-1968 (Box 1)
        [1-8]
      - 1968-1972 (Box 1)
        [1-9]
      - 1973-1976 (Box 1)
        [1-10]
      - 1977-1979 (Box 1)
        [1-11]
  - Michigan Athletic Department Policies 1966 (Box 1)
    [1-12]
  - Michigan Calendar Problems in the Big Ten
    - 1958, 1961 (Reports and Correspondence) (Box 1)
      [1-13]
    - 1964-1965 (Correspondence) (Box 1)
      [1-14]
  - Michigan Presidents' Files
    - President Fleming (Box 1)
      [1-15]
    - President Hatcher (Box 1)
      [1-16]
  - Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SAC)
    - 1956/57-1959/60 (Box 1)
      [1-17]
    - 1960/61-1964/65 (Box 1)
      [1-18]
    - 1969/70-1977/78 (Box 1)
      [1-19]
    - Special Committee on Professionalism (Box 1)
      [1-20]
  - Scholastic Eligibility
    - Committee on Academic Performance 1956-1979 (Box 1)
      [1-21]
    - Michigan's Certification of Academic Requirement 1960-1967 (Box 1)
      [1-22]
    - Transfers: Cross Campus LSA and School of Education (Box 1)
      [1-23]
  - Special Michigan Problems
    - Band Problems 1975-1976 (Box 2)
      [2-1]
    - Canham Article Sports Illustrated, 1975 (Box 2)
      [2-2]
    - Ferguson Scholarship Fund (Box 2)
      [2-3]
    - Fielding H. Yost Award (Box 2)
      [2-4]
    - Program for Culturally Deprived (Box 2)
      [2-5]
    - Ray Fisher Award (Box 2)
      [2-6]
    - Special Committee on Recruiting 1975-1976 (Box 2)
      [2-7]
    - Tenure of Coaches (Box 2)
      [2-8]
    - Tutoring Programs (Box 2)
      [2-9]
    - University of Michigan Ann Arbor Alumni Club-Summer Employment (Box 2)
      [2-10]
- Big Ten Conference
  The records of the Big Ten Conference were collected by Plant during his tenure as the University of Michigan's faculty representative to the Big Ten (1955-1979). These records include correspondence and minutes of the Council of Ten (the ten university presidents); recommendations and decisions concerning financial aid plans; interpretations and opinions of Conference rules and regulations; and records relating to women's athletics.
  - Council of Ten-Big Ten Presidents
    - Economy Measures 1975 (Box 2)
      [2-11]
    - Jurisdictional Measures (Box 2)
      [2-12]
    - Report of the Commissioner to the Council of Ten
      - 1972-1973 (Box 2)
        [2-13]
      - 1974-1975 (Box 2)
        [2-14]
      - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
        [2-15]
      - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
        [2-16]
  - Financial Aid Plans in the Big Ten
    - 1956-1958 (Box 2)
      [2-17]
    - 1959-1960 (Box 2)
      [2-18]
    - 1961 (Box 2)
      [2-19]
    - 1962 (Box 2)
      [2-20]
    - 1963-1964 (Box 2)
      [2-21]
    - 1965-1968 (Box 2)
      [2-22]
    - 1969-1972 (Box 2)
      [2-23]
    - 1973-1978 (Box 2)
      [2-24]
  - Handbook of the Intercollegiate (Big Ten) Conference 1979 (Box 2)
    [2-25]
  - Interpretations and Opinions of Conference Rules; Regulations and Agreements; and Procedures Memorandum 1965-1975 (Box 2)
    [2-26]
  - Special Committee on Financial Aid (Box 2)
    [2-27]
  - Women's Athletics
    - University of Michigan
      - 1973-1975 (Box 2)
        [2-28]
      - 1976-1979 (Box 2)
        [2-29]
      - Procedure Manual for Women's Athletics (Box 2)
        [2-30]
    - Big Ten Conference
      - 1974-1975 (Box 2)
        [2-31]
      - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
        [2-32]
      - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
        [2-33]
    - NCAA 1972-1979 (Box 2)
      [2-34]
- NCAA
  The records of the NCAA (1961 to 1980) are particularly complete during Plant's NCAA presidential term, 1967 to 1969. The files contain materials on the NCAA-AAU controversy, correspondence, Executive committee minutes, minutes of the NCAA Council, and topical files.
  - AAU Controversy
    - 1961-1965 (Box 3)
      [3-1]
    - 1966 (Box 3)
      [3-2]
    - 1967
      - Correspondence
        - January-February (Box 3)
          [3-3]
        - March (Box 3)
          [3-4]
        - April-May (Box 3)
          [3-5]
        - June-September (Box 3)
          [3-6]
        - October-December (Box 3)
          [3-7]
      - Senate Hearings (Box 3)
        [3-8]
      - Sherman Anti Trust (Box 3)
        [3-9]
    - 1968
      - Athlete's Bill of Rights (Box 3)
        [3-10]
      - Awards and Rejections (Box 3)
        [3-11]
      - Correspondence
        - January-February (Box 3)
          [3-13]
        - March-April (Box 3)
          [3-14]
        - May (Box 3)
          [3-15]
        - June-December (Box 3)
          [3-16]
      - Press Reaction (Box 3)
      - Report: The Track and Field Rebellion (Box 3)
        [3-18]
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
        [3-19]
    - 1969-1972 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - 1965-1966 (Box 3)
      [4-1]
    - 1967
      - January (Box 4)
        [4-2]
      - February-March (Box 4)
        [4-3]
      - April-May (Box 4)
        [4-4]
      - June-August (Box 4)
        [4-5]
      - September-October (Box 4)
        [4-6]
      - November-December (Box 4)
        [4-7]
    - 1968
      - January (Box 4)
        [4-8]
      - February (Box 4)
        [4-9]
      - March (Box 4)
        [4-10]
      - April (Box 4)
        [4-11]
      - May-June (Box 4)
        [4-12]
      - July-August (Box 4)
        [4-13]
      - September (Box 4)
        [4-14]
      - October (Box 4)
        [4-15]
      - November (Box 4)
        [4-16]
      - December (Box 4)
        [4-17]
    - 1969 (Box 4)
      [4-18]
    - 1970-1971 (Box 4)
      [4-19]
    - 1974-1975 (Box 4)
      [4-20]
    - 1976-1977 (Box 4)
      [4-21]
    - 1977-1978 (Box 4)
      [4-22]
    - 1979-1980 (Box 4)
      [4-23]
  - Executive Committee Minutes (Box 5)
    - 1969 (Box 5)
      [5-1]
    - 1970 (Box 5)
      [5-2]
    - 197T1 (Box 5)
      [5-3]
    - 1972 (Box 5)
      [5-4]
    - 1973 (Box 5)
      [5-5]
  - Legal Programs
    - Basketball Lawsuits
      - NCAA v. Howard Porter and the ABA (Box 5)
        [5-6]
      - Robert L. Parish v. NCAA (Box 5)
        [5-7]
    - Hockey Lawsuits
      - Buckton and Marzo v. NCAA (Box 5)
        [5-8]
      - Jones v. NCAA (Box 5)
        [5-9]
      - Special Committee on Canadian Hockey Players (Box 5)
        [5-10]
    - Legal Attaches on Rulings on Student Eligibility (Box 5)
      [5-11]
    - Profession Football Telecasts in Violation of PL87-331 (Box 5)
      [5-12]
    - Student-Athletes Conduct-Clenched Fist Salute (Box 5)
      [5-13]
    - Track and Field Lawsuit (Samara v. NCAA) (Box 5)
      [5-14]
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
      [5-15]
  - Minutes of the Council
    - 1967 (Box 5)
      [5-16]
    - 1968
      - January-August (Box 5)
        [5-17]
      - September-December (Box 5)
        [5-18]
    - 1969 (Box 5)
      [5-19]
  - Telephone Conferences 1967-1968 (Box 5)
    [5-20]
  - Topical Files
    - College Football Association (Box 5)
      [5-21]
    - Committee on Accelerated Academic Programs (Box 5)
      [5-22]
    - Congressional Investigation of NCAA Infraction Procedures (Box 5)
      [5-23]
    - 1.600 Legislation
      - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 5)
        [5-24-26]
      - Plant-Kingman Papers (Box 6)
        [6-1]
      - Revision of the 1968 Convention (Box 6)
        [6-2]
    - Proposal for Need and Number Limitations on Grants of Financial Aid, 2 folders (Box 6)
      [6-3-4]
    - Reorganization of Division I Football (Box 6)
      [6-5]
    - Roving Championship Committee (Box 6)
      [6-6]
    - Special Matters
      - Central College-Waynesburg College (Box 6)
        [6-7]
      - Clippings (Box 6)
        [6-8]
      - Committee on Recruiting (Box 6)
        [6-9]
      - Committee to Study National Championship (Box 6)
        [6-10]
      - Football Practice Starting Date 1967 Study (Box 6)
        [6-11]
      - NCAA Report (Box 6)
        [6-12]
      - Special Committee on Hockey (Box 6)
        [6-13]
      - Theodore Roosevelt Award 1969 (Box 6)
        [6-14]
    - Survey on Gambling in Sports (Box 6)
      [6-15]
    - Television Revenue: Long Beach State Proposal 1975 (Box 6)
      [6-16]
    - United States Naval Academy (Box 6)
      [6-17]
- Western Intercollegiate Hockey League
  The records of the Western Intercollegiate Hockey League include the history and minutes of the league, correspondence, and materials concerning Canadian students' eligibility.
  - History and Minutes (Box 6)
    [6-18]
  - Canadian Eligibility
    - Case Studies, 2 folders (Box 6)
      [6-19-20]
    - Special NCAA Committee, 3 folders (Box 6)
      [6-21-23]
  - Correspondence 1953-1957 (Box 6)
    [6-24]
- Western Collegiate Hockey Association
  Western Collegiate Hockey Association (WCHA) records consist of organizational papers, correspondence and papers concerning the WCHA realignment, and the NCAA's investigation of the Midwest Junior Hockey League.
  - Organizational Papers (Box 7)
    [7-1]
  - Articles of Agreement (Box 7)
    [7-2]
  - Correspondence
    - 1958-1974 (Box 7)
      [7-3]
    - 19T4/1975 (Box 7)
      [7-4]
    - 1975/76 (Box 7)
      [7-5]
  - 1976/77-1978/79 (Box 7)
    [7-6]
  - Hockey Realignment (Box 7)
    [7-7]
  - Midwest Junior League NCAA Investigation, 2 folders (Box 7)
    [7-8-9]
- United States Olympic Committee
  The materials of the United States Olympic Committee were collected by Plant while he was a member of the Committee (1969-1972). The records consist of administrative files; and papers relating to the Committee for a Better Olympics, the Committee on Eligibility Olympic Committee matters, and the President's Commission on Olympic Sports.
  - Administrative Files
    - Biennial Meeting; 1971 (Box 7)
      [7-10]
    - Board of Directors; October 1971 (Box 7)
      [7-11]
    - Director's Meeting 1972 (Box 7)
      [7-12]
    - Financial Reports 1971, 1972 (Box 7)
      [7-13]
    - Fund Raising (Box 7)
      [7-14]
    - Minutes 1969-1970 (Box 7)
      [7-15]
    - NCAA Olympic Committee Matters (Box 7)
      [7-16]
    - NCAA Withdrawal from the USOC (Box 7)
      [7-17]
    - Organizational Papers (Box 7)
      [7-18]
  - Committee for a Better Olympics
    - New Structure (Box 7)
      [7-19]
    - Proceedings December 1972 (Box 7)
      [7-20]
    - Proceedings February 1973 (Box 7)
      [7-21]
  - Committee on Eligibility (Box 8)
    - Chairman's Memorandum (Box 8)
      [8-1]
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 8)
      [8-2, 3]
    - Documents and Materials (Box 8)
      [8-4]
    - Draft Report to Board (Box 8)
      [8-5]
    - International Olympic Committee (Box 8)
      [8-6]
    - Press Stories (Box 8)
      [8-7]
    - Proposals for Amendments (Box 8)
      [8-8]
  - Olympic Committee Matters
    - Basketball Federation (Box 8)
      [8-9]
    - United States Track and Field Federation (Box 8)
      [8-10]
    - Wrestling Federation, 2 folders (Box 8)
      [8-11, 12]
    - President's Commission on Olympic Sports (Box 8)
      [8-13]
- Law School
  - Centennial Observance of the law School of the University of Michigan 1959 (Box 8)
    (correspondence and notes)
- Photographs (Box 8)
  The Photographs series includes images from ceremonies relating to celebration of the centennial of the University of Michigan Law School; photos of faculty used in centennial observance publications; and miscellaneous photos of Plant at meetings.